Welcome to our third lecture on
Respiratory Physiology.
Today, we're going
to explore pulmonary
circulation.
Once again, Dr. Jörg Lehest.
The session objectives are in
line with the
event description.
This event encompasses
the setup and physiology
of the two blood circulatory
systems, pulmonary
and bronchio, supplying
the respiratory system.
Much of this event
focuses on the regulation
of pulmonary blood
flow in response to
vascular resistance,
gravity, and physiological
vasoconstrictors
and vasodilators.
The meaning of lymphatic
flow and ensuring proper
exchange of solvent and
solutes will also be discussed.
The lungs are uniquely
set up with a blood supply
by having two circulatory
systems. The one is
the pulmonary system, the
other one is the bronchial
system the pulmonary
system operates at a low
mean arterial pressure
going in at about 14
millimeters mercury whereas
the bronchial system
which is part of the
systemic circulation comes
in at 90 millimeters mercury
just a reminder that's
how the mean arterial
pressure is determined
reflecting that the
blood spends more time in
the diastolic phase than
in the systolic phase
just be aware that there
are other formulas as
well which you might be
taught in other classes
one of the biggest
questions might be how since
both systems work at such
different operating pressures
how an equal blood flow
can be achieved and
that has much to do with
the compliance so the
pulmonary system uses
vessels that are much more
compliant so they are much
more distensible and compliant
to blood flow, thereby
providing less resistance
to blood flow. And we're
going to talk about
this in more detail, whereas
the bronchial system,
the vessels that are
involved in the bronchial
system don't have that
kind of compliance.
So to give you some numbers,
at any point in time,
about half a liter,
which is 500 milliliters
of blood resides in the lungs
and about 70 milliliters
in capillaries at any
given point in time.
This slide of the bronchovascular
bundle illustrates
neatly all of the components
that are involved with
lung physiology on a
microscopical structural level.
So here we have a main
bronchus. You already know
by seeing that their
cartilage piece is around it,
that this is before
generation 10, which we talked
about a few lectures
back. At the same time, we
find a pulmonary artery
here and a pulmonary vein.
We find a bronchial artery
here. You can appreciate
that the bronchial
arteries are much smaller.
These arteries need, they're
large enough, however,
that they need their own blood
supply. That's
called vasovasorum.
You can also appreciate
that there are
autonomic nerve fibers
that are running
along all of these
blood vessels.
And as we discussed
before, that's because
there's an interface with
the autonomic nervous
system, sympathetic or
parasympathetic branch,
for regulation of
blood vessel diameter.
And those are the nerve strands
that supply this innervation.
In addition, we have
lymphatic vessels
here. You can see
them here and here.
they ensure that
the interstitial
space is not overly
filled with liquid.
When it does do that, then
the perivascular potential
space fills up with
additional liquid, so then
that we call an edema, and that
can lead to various
pathologies.
So there, for instance,
lymphoid granulomas that can
ensue or primary pulmonary
lymphomas, but those are
pathologies that you will
cover in other lectures.
This cross-section at
the level of the alveoli
neatly demonstrates why
this area has been called a
sheet of blood by many. So
this is a highly vascularized
system, which has about
200, features about 280
billion capillaries for 300
million alveoli, which if
you do the math, means that
each alveolus is served by
several hundred and to up
to a thousand capillaries.
so that's an enormous
amount of vascular
supply so the that
increases the surface of gas
for gas exchange to a
tremendous level and people have
calculated this to be about
70 to 80 meters square
which is about 800 square
feet and that size occupies
about five parking spaces.
So you read frequently about
the size of a tennis court
but it's actually not that
large and it doesn't need
to be but it's still huge.
So for a red blood cell to
passage the system it has
to actually squeeze because
some of these vessels are
so small they are only six
micrometers in diameter
and a red blood cell is
about eight micrometer so it
will only be able to passage
when it squeezes a little
bit, which puts additional
stress on the red blood
cells, and that's part of
why they also wear out after
time, but there are other
reasons for that as well.
It takes a red blood cell
about 0.75 or three quarters
of a second to passage the
system, and by that time,
under normal physiologic
conditions, all of the oxygen
has been exchanged also
the carbon dioxide so that
happens about one third way
through the system and but
that changes with certain
pathologies so pulmonary blood
flow can be quickly adjusted
from about three and a
half liters per minute per
meter square of body surface
to 25 that's about eight
times more within a jiffy
And that means that
instead of having only 70
milliliters of blood in
the pulmonary capillary
system at a time,
there's going to be about
200. So now, how can
this happen so quickly?
So here, looking at a
cross-section of pulmonary
capillaries, and you can
appreciate that some of them are
conducting and others are
closed. There's no blood
flowing here. So there are
two ways that the blood flow
can be increased quickly.
The one is additional
before quiescent capillaries
can be opened up. That
process is called recruitment
and the other process that
makes this possible is that
capillaries can open up
that are already open can
open up further and that
process is called distension.
So the answer to how this
is possible that blood flow
can adjust be adjusted so
quickly is twofold, its
recruitment and distension.
What's noteworthy at
this point is that
despite the increased
blood flow and regardless
of the mechanism
that's being used,
there's no significant
increase in
vascular resistance
in the lungs.
You might ask how that
is possible, but that is
possible because of parallel
flow versus serial flow.
So that means that by opening
up more blood vessels,
for instance, as in
recruitment, there are more
parallel ways to shuttle
the blood along, and
there's no chance of building
up additional pressure.
So because there are more
new options where the
blood can flow, which
prevents additional pressure.
So the capillaries
themselves are very hard to
manipulate. So the
manipulation that accommodates
a higher level of
activity and blood flow
actually happens at the
level of the pulmonary
arteries and veins,
and those that are
approximately 50 micrometers
in diameter or more,
because only those
have smooth muscle.
So pulmonary arterioles
and capillaries, they do
not have smooth muscle.
And that is because
especially the capillaries
are involved in gas exchange,
so there's no room for
muscle, no need. Again,
the main regulation,
main sympathetic regulation,
which increases the
diameter of these capillaries
in the end, that happens
to regulation at the
pulmonary arteries and veins.
You can see them right
here. So there's a pulmonary
vein that brings oxygen
-poor blood into the
alveoli. You can see how
interlaced it is with
vasomotor nerves, and
the same is true for the
pulmonary veins that carry
the oxygenated blood.
One thing I would like
to point out in terms of
the bronchial system is
that the bronchial artery
anatomy can vary from person
to person. So it either
springs from the aorta
or from the intercostal
arteries and in most cases
it has three branches
that come off the above
vessels, and in some cases
it has four, so in their
various type, and here you
have the percentages how
frequently they occur.
There are a few things
that are unique about the
bronchial circulation,
and I'm calling it back
up, and I will explain in
a second. So the bronchial
circulation is peculiar
because it only goes
down to the level of the
terminal bronchioles.
that's approximately here
and but it supplies all
structures until then so
that includes on the very top
the trachea and airways
larger airways pulmonary
blood vessels we talked
about vasovasorum visceral
pleurum lymph nodes and the
cells that make up the lymph
nodes and also the cells
that are involved with
the parasympathetic nervous
supply and its branches.
So then, at the level of
the alveoli, the pulmonary
circulation takes
over, and it supplies a
mixed venous blood, which
then has its CO2 removed
and has oxygen added
from the alveolar air.
So once this reoxygenated
blood leaves the alveoli,
then it's being mixed
through shunts. We
talked about this with
the bronchopulmonary,
via bronchopulmonary
anastomosis and veins
with the bronchial
circulation. So in other
words, two-thirds
of the oxygen-poor
bronchial circulation
runs via shuns into the
pulmonary
circulation, which has
just been resupplied
with oxygen.
The rest of the blood from
the bronchial circulation
disappears via the ozygous
and hemiozygous and
then into via the intercostal
veins from the system.
And one thing that is
noteworthy is that in cases
of lung transplantations,
it has been found that
the pulmonary circulation
is actually sufficient
to supply all of these
structures plus the alveoli
with blood. So, in that
sense, the bronchial
circulation is nice to
have, and probably having
it allows an organism to
be more efficient around
its metabolism and its
activities, but in the
end, it's only thought of
as a backup circulation.
So, the system can, if
it has to, do without.
Another advantage of having
two systems that run in
parallel is the reduction
of the risk of embolisms.
So even if an embolism forms
in one of the system and
occludes an area which would
otherwise starve the area
for blood supply, the other
system can cover for it.
When considering pulmonary
blood flow, one has to
further consider pulmonary
vascular resistance, or PVR.
That indicates the
difficulty of shuttling
blood through the
pulmonary circulation,
and that process is
influenced by gravity, can
be influenced by alveolar
pressure, so that's
the air pressure inside
the alveoli, which
can, depending on how
strong it is, squeeze the
underlying capillary
blood vessels shut, and
also the arterial to
venous pressure gradient.
So there is a formula that's
called the Poiseuil's law
that can be used to
determine what the resistance
looks like. So Poiseuil's law
indicates that the resistance
is the quotient between
pressure at the beginning
of a tube, that's P1, minus
the pressure at the end
of a tube, that's p2, divided
by the flow which is q.
Now to transposing this
to our situation in the
respiratory system, that
leads us to pulmonary vascular
resistance being the quotient
of the pressure in the
pulmonary artery that brings
blood into the pulmonary
system minus the pressure
in the left atrium, which
is where the oxygenated
blood is supplied to,
divided by cardiac output,
which is the flow indicator.
In the normal circumstances,
and you can look the
numbers up here in this
image, which I've also shown
in the previous slide,
if you plug them in, then
the pressure in the
pulmonary artery is about 14
millimeters mercury the
pressure in the left our
atrium where the oxygenated
blood is going is about
eight millimeters mercury
and that divided by an
average of six liters of
blood flowing through the
pulmonary system per minute
and that ends up being
about one millimeter
mercury per liter per minute
of resistance in the pulmonary
system, which is about
10 times less than the
resistance in systemic
circulation, which works
at a much higher pressure.
The only thing about
blood flow in the lungs is
actually, and you can
see this from this graph,
is that as blood flow
increases along the x-axis,
pulmonary vascular resistance
actually goes down.
So at rest, about
one-third of the
resistance that can be measured
comes from the
resistance in arterioles,
one-third capillaries,
one-third in veins.
And as I said, as
blood flow increases,
for instance, through
increased demand,
the pulmonary vascular
resistance actually goes
down. So that's how this
is very different than
the systemic circulation.
So why is this the case?
Well, we talked about
this before, and
it has much to do
with recruitment and
distension. So as
blood flow increases,
more and more parallel
pathways are opened
up, as you can see
through recruitment.
And even if no parallel
pathways are opened up,
the ones that are already
open through distension,
they're being widened.
So the blood that comes
in through this way here
has many, many options
to flow through the system,
and that just generally
keeps the pressure down,
and it even reduces
it further as the system
opens up more. And that's
what makes pulmonary
blood flow in terms of
resistance very different
than systemic blood flow.
Gravity has a significant
effect on pulmonary
blood flow, especially
when considering the height
of the lung, which is
about 10 centimeters.
So gravity pulls so much
on the blood that's,
or the liquid in general,
that is in the lungs,
that the bottom of
the lungs receives the
largest amount of blood.
And the top of the
lungs, the apex, receives
the smallest amount.
So the blood flow
per alveolus at the
bottom is much,
much larger than the
blood flow per
alveolus at the top.
Per centimeter, the additional
pressure that it takes to
overcome one centimeter
in additional height is
about 0.74 millimeters
mercury. And across the
entire height of the lungs,
which is, as I said, is
10 centimeters, That is a
difference of 7.4 millimeters
mercury that it takes to
put blood through the top
compared to the bottom.
So just remember that
the pressures inside the
pulmonary circulations
are already very low.
and the pressure at the
left atrium where the blood
is coming in from the lungs
after being oxygenated
is only 8 millimeters
mercury to begin with.
So the 7.4 are a huge
force to work against
trying to get blood through
the apex of the lungs.
So this slide
illustrates the effect of
gravity on an upright
lung and compares the flow
through the three
zones, zone 1, 2 and 3.
Zone 1 being the apex and zone
3 being the base of the lung.
These zones are also
referred to as zones of west.
So in the first part of
our example, the alveolar
pressure designated by P
capital A is larger than both
the arterial as well as
the venous pressure and
in that situation the artery
or arterioles that supply
blood to the pulmonary
capillaries always squeezed
shut so very little to
no blood can get through
and that's that impedes blood
flow in zone 1. Now that
there's no blood flow
at all typically doesn't
happen under normal physiologic
conditions, but there
are pathological conditions
where that is the case.
Zone 2 is the middle portion
and to get blood up there
from the pulmonary artery
is much easier because it
has to be worked less against
gravity. So in this situation,
the pulmonary arterial
pressure is the largest.
It's larger than pulmonary
alveolar pressure. It's larger
than pulmonary venous pressure.
And in this situation,
we get biphasic blood
flow. So where blood flows
during systole, and blood
doesn't flow during diastole.
here at the bottom of the
lungs we have the third
situation that's zone 3 and
in this case the pulmonary
arterial blood flow always
has the highest pressure
larger than pulmonary
venous pulmonary alveolar
pressure and so here the
blood supply is always
open the capillary is
always supplied and there's
always blood flow occurring
at the base of the lung.
Now the situation changes
when the position turns
from upright to supine, then
these zones disappear and
everything becomes equal.
Next two slides, we are
going to explore the effect
of pressures on extra and
alveolar vessels. So let's
start with the extra alveolar
vessels, which are the
larger vessels. They're
typically not directly associated
with individual alveoli,
so you can see this here.
And here the pressure
inside the alveoli has very
little effect. So they're
all inflated, as you can see,
so there's high pressure
in there. But if anything,
their opening actually
increases the blood flow of
those extra alveolar
vessels. So those are larger
vessels that supply the
lung tissue, and the reason
this is happening is due
to radial traction. So all
of these alveoli, they are
connected, and when one
opens, it becomes more
likely that another one of
the neighboring one opens as
well, and the same happens
with the larger blood
vessels that run through.
So, the resistance is
therefore high at low
lung volumes when all
of these alveoli are
collapsed, and is low
at volumes where at high
alveolar volumes when
they're all expanded. And
as I said, that is due
to the radial traction.
Alveolar pressure
has a profound effect
on alveolar vessels
and those are the
types of alveolar vessels.
They're called the intra
-alveolar vessels. It
would be right here,
here, here, here, part of
this hexagon, and then
there are septal vessels.
And so this is an alveolus
with a low volume,
and these capillaries are
engorged with blood. And
as the alveolar walls
stretch with the adoption of
higher volume, those blood
vessels get squeezed.
So at low lung volumes,
the resistance of
these alveolar vessels
is low, and at high
lung volumes, as in
this situation here,
the resistance due
to squeezing is high.
The total pulmonary
vascular resistance
is a combination
effect of extra
pulmonary and pulmonary
blood vessels.
And you can see here at the
spirogram that the
overall effect,
overall resistance is the
lowest at functional residual
capacity. So that's right
here, and that's the volume
when we just expired here.
So this is tidal volume,
inspiration, expiration.
When tidal volume has
been expired, that is
when we see the lowest
vascular resistance in
the respiratory system.
If we go below that,
then due to the effect of
the extra pulmonary blood
vessels that experience
increased resistance with
lower volumes, we see
an increase in pulmonary
vascular resistance.
If we increase
the volume towards
total lung capacity.
It's right here.
Due to the effect of pulmonary
blood vessels and the
diminished effect of extra
pulmonary blood vessels
because they're just
outnumbered, the overall alveolar
resistance, vessel resistance
increases dramatically.
So when supplying positive
pressure mechanical
ventilation, as in many
of the more extreme
COVID-19 cases, one has
to be very, very careful
to properly adjust the
equipment because an
increase in alveolar
pressure by the machine will
also lead to a decrease
in transmural pressure.
So transmural pressure is
the pressure that exists
between the inside of
the lung and the outside.
And as we have seen in
the previous slides, what
can happen is that if
the alveolar pressure is
adjusted too high, it can
actually squeeze shut any
blood supply to the lung
or to a lung area and
turn this into a zone
one problem so as we have
explored at the apex of the
lung in zone one of west
so these machines are
very carefully calibrated
and in relation to the
person that they're
being used with
and they're closely
monitored because of
this zone one risk
this slide depicts an example
of the alveolar capillary
network and as we previously
said one alveolus is
served by several hundred
and up to a thousand little
capillary blood vessels
there's something else that
is unique about these blood
vessels actually the interface
of the blood vessel with
the alveolus so this is
the alveolus with the
alveolar space filled with air
here we have the
endothelial cells lining
the capillary blood
vessel and you can see
that here on the sides
there is a structure
that's considered the
basement membrane so the
basement membrane has
different functions but one
of it is that it acts
as a scaffolding like an
attachment sites to
which cells can stably
adhere, and it produces
thereby kind of rigidity.
So you can see that these
two cell types, so here
type 1 pneumocyte and
here capillary endothelial
cell, they share this
basement membrane. So usually
each of those cells would
have their own basement
membrane, But inside the
alveolar capillary network,
these cell types, they
share a basal membrane.
And you guessed it, that is to
keep diffusion distances small.
And getting gases across
one or two micrometers is
much easier than as if there
were two basal membranes
to overcome. So this arrow
here indicates the flow of
oxygen from the alveolar
space into the capillary,
and this arrow here indicates
the movement of carbon
dioxide from the bloodstream
into the alveolar space.
um one thing that we've
already mentioned before once
as well is that um you
know there is damage that
occurs here there's a lot of
wear and tear um and these
type 1 pneumocytes they
can wear out and when that
happens a type 2 pneumocytes
which also reduces the
surfactant it will come
along and those are the
green cells here and they
will then because they have
stem cell qualities they
will then differentiate into
a type 1 pneumocyte and
replace the broken cell it's
important to consider that
not only gases have to
flow across the alveolar
capillary network but also
solvents and solutes so
our universal solute water
for instance has to penetrate
everywhere it's needed
and then some important
salts such as sodium chloride
urea and also our universal
energy carrier glucose
um they're only limited
by the fact how quickly
the capillaries can get
them into their position
so they fit through all
of the spaces they have
no chemical modifications
that would hold them
back And that is what
we call flow limited.
So the flow of blood into this
particular area is
what limits them.
And in terms of diffusion, they
can get anywhere they need to.
That is very different
with certain large
molecules. They may be
too large to fit through
certain pores. They may
have chemical modifications
that make them bulky
or that repel them.
So those molecules we
call diffusion limited.
Then we have lipid-soluble
molecules, believe it or
not, but both oxygen and carbon
dioxide are lipid-soluble,
and they have to be because
they have to flow across
or diffuse across all of
these plasma membranes here
between the capillaries
and the cells, the type 1
pneumocytes that make up the
alveous. So, here's where
diffusion happens, and diffusion,
there's certain mechanisms
that are, in addition to
what we just discussed,
involved in the transport of
molecules. One is filtration,
and so those are molecules
that are filtered through
pores, and whether they're
filtered or not depends
on the hydrostatic versus
oncotic pressure. So, we'll
discuss this in a little
bit more detail in one of
the later lectures, but
hydrostatic pressure is the
blood pressure inside the
capillary, and the larger
that pressure, the more
molecules that are filterable
can be filtered through
this filtration apparatus.
Oncotic pressure is
the attraction that
charged molecules
exert on other charged
molecules that are
in the bloodstream.
um the class of molecules
that provide the most
charges in the bloodstream
are large proteins
such as albumin so they
work like little magnets
holding things back that
want to get filtered
into the alveolar space for
instance and then lastly
we need to consider penocytosis
so that's a specific
mechanism it's also called
cell drinking and through
the mechanism of penocytosis
very large molecules
or 30 nanometers is huge
in terms of molecular size
they can be actually moved
in little vesicles from
one side to the next well
you may ask well how can
things be moved because
here on this side that I'm
showing right now that's
where air is located and
inside the blood vessel we
have blood which is a liquid
well you have to consider
that all living cells
need to be covered with
liquid. So it's not true to
say that these molecules
that are in the bloodstream
are going directly from a
liquid phase into an air
phase. They actually go from
a liquid phase here into
the liquid film that
overlays those cells here in
the alveus. So they're
going from liquid to liquid.
The pulmonary lymphatic
system is very important
for respiratory function
because it clears away
interstitial fluid into the
lymphatic system and then
into the subclavian vein
and it takes care of
about 30 milliliters of
interstitial fluid per hour.
Without it there would
be huge edema in the
peribronchial space and that
is inconsistent with life.
So here you can see the
two forces again that are
responsible for filtration
and the production of this
interstitial fluid. So here
we have the hydrostatic
force, a hydrostatic force,
which pushes liquid out
of the blood vessel into the
surrounding parent bronchial
interstitial space. And
then we have the oncotic
pressure, which, as I said,
is exerted by charges,
mostly on large protein
molecules that points the
opposite way. Overall, the
winner is typically the
hydrostatic pressure and
that's why we end up with this
interstitial fluid at all
times that would accumulate
if it wasn't for the work
of the lymphatic system.
How much a pulmonary system
tends to the formation of
edema depends on the size
of the hydrostatic pressure
versus the oncotic pressure,
and that can be calculated
with the so-called Starling
equation. Again, it's
important to me that you
understand what the contributors
are, more so than being
able to plug in numbers.
So the fluid flow is
determined by the hydrostatic
pressure minus the oncotic
pressure and the hydrostatic
pressure is determined by
the capillary filtration
coefficient times intravascular
hydrostatic pressure
minus interstitial
hydrostatic pressure so these
two terms here are the
poles on either side so the
intravascular capillary
hydrostatic pressure is
pushing liquid out of the
capillary. The interstitial
hydrostatic pressure wants
to push liquid from the
interstitial space into
the capillary, so the two
opposing forces multiplied
by the capillary filtration
coefficient. The same we
have on the oncotic side.
There we have what's
called a lowercase sigma,
Stabermann's reflection
coefficient, so that is basically
the reflection of charged
molecules from going inside
the blood vessel. I told
you that's inside the
majority of the oncotic
pressure that exists, works into
the blood vessel, into
that direction, and that's
because there is a large
number of charged proteins.
that are moving along
with the blood flow.
Any molecules in the
interstitium that are charged,
they will be reflected
by the charges that are
already inside the blood
vessel. So that makes
up the Staverman's
reflection coefficient. And
then again, we have the
colloid osmotic pressure,
which is inside the vascular
system, which pulls things
into the blood vessel. We
have the interstitial called
osmotic pressure, which
is charged molecules that
are interstitium that are
pulling other charged molecules
into the interstitium. So
those two are also going
into opposite directions, and
the three of them together
make up the forces that
define the oncotic pressure.
So depending on how
large each of one are,
how hydrostatic
pressure compares to
oncotic pressure, one
can calculate what the
fluid flux is using
the Starling equation.
One of the main
reasons for pulmonary
edema is left-sided
heart dysfunction,
so left-sided ventricular
infarction or mitral
stenosis, like stiffening
of the mitral valve
on the left side of the
heart. And if that happens,
then the blood cannot be
sufficiently cleared
from the left side of the
heart. So, and then when
blood tries to return
through the pulmonary vein
to the left atrium, there's
backflow and back pressure,
So then blood cannot
sufficiently clear through
the left atrium and left
ventricle back into the
system. So this additional
pressure then produces
back pressure into the
pulmonary capillaries. And
with that, there's a lot
more filtration going on.
And additional liquid ends
up in the alveoli, which
are impeded to facilitate
or to carry out an efficient
exchange of gases due
to the increased diffusion
distance through all of
this liquid. And that's,
of course, a huge problem.
One very powerful way to
shift blood supply inside
the lung is through
hypoxic vasoconstriction.
constriction. The name
already indicates how
this works and you can
see it here on the graph.
So areas that are very well
ventilated, good alveolar
PO2, they also have
high blood flow, that's
here, and areas that are
very poorly ventilated,
which would be here, also
have reduced blood flow.
So by using this mechanism,
our body ensures that
areas that are very well
ventilated receive the most
blood flow, which maximizes
the overall result.
Now by shutting some blood
flow off, considering that
we want to maintain a low
resistance in the blood
flow to and through the
lungs, then the risk always
becomes of a higher
resistance and that the heart
has to work harder and then
over time sustains damage.
But this effect of hypoxic
vasoconstriction only
becomes measurable in
terms of resistance when
more than 20% of the
vessels are affected by it.
There's one problem with
high altitude, so in high
altitude situations
with very low air oxygen
levels, this process of
hypoxic vasoconstriction can
apply to the entire lung,
and that of course is
a huge problem. So, but
we're going to talk about
that more in one of the
subsequent lectures, what
it means to breathe in
high altitude situations.
Here's a list, and there
are several lists, and
they're all different
across the literature,
that I consider the most
prominent local factors
that influence
vasoconstriction or dilation
of airways. And one is
the group of endothelins
Endothelins are potent
vasoconstrictors
They're made by endothelial
cells And they're
made in response to
shear stress and hypoxia
There's the group of
thrombex, thromboxanes
Especially thromboxane A2
is a potent vasoconstrictor
Tromboxanes are all derivatives
of arachnidonic acid
And they are produced by
white blood cells, such as
macrophages and megarkaryocytes,
which give rise to
platelets Then there is
the group of prostacyclins
They are actually
potent vasodilators,
so is nitric oxide,
that's a vasodilator
and then there's another
group of the leukotrients.
Those are inflammatory
mediators and
they're also potent airway
constrictors. So this
is not a complete list.
This is a select list,
but you should know these
and have heard of those
as modulators of
vasoconstriction or dilation.
And here another WorldStar
practice question
for you. A healthy 22
-year-old military recruit
stands completely
upright and motionless at
attention during a
prolonged morning formation.
Due to the effects of
gravity on hydrostatic
column pressure within
the pulmonary vasculature,
the distribution of blood
varies significantly
from the apex to the
base of her lungs.
Which of the following
statements best
describes the structural
and pressure relationships
occurring specifically
at the apex, which
is zone of west number
one, of her lungs,
while she is standing upright
i'll let you look over the
answer choices and it should
be fairly easy for you okay
let's go through alveolar
pressure is lower than both
pulmonary arterial and
venous pressure maximizing
regional perfusion that's
choice A, and that's wrong
because if anything,
alveolar pressure is higher
than any pressure that
depends on gravity pulling on
blood going through the lungs.
So that's the hydrostatic
pressure. So at the
top of the lungs, the
hydrostatic pressure is low,
and at the bottom it's high.
So alveolar pressure,
if anything, is higher
than both pulmonary
arterial or venous
pressure. Pulmonary
arterial or venous pressure.
B, pulmonary arterial
pressure is highly
elevated by gravity,
causing capillary
engorgement and
maximum gas exchange.
That's kind of what's
going on at the base of the
lung but not the top and
as i said before with
a it has to do with the
hydrostatic pressure of
blood being influenced by
gravity pulling it down
just to reiterate the
apex the top of the lung
sits above the heart so
the heart has to pump very
hard to get any blood
into the top of the lungs
And therefore, A
and B are false.
Pulmonary, that's D now,
venous pressure, exceeds
alveolar pressure,
keeping the vessel fully open
regardless of the
arterial pressure.
Once again, that's not true
because of
hydrostatic pressure.
E, hydrostatic pressure
is at its absolute
highest, at the apex
that would be, causing
the apical lymphatics
to overflow and match
the base of the lung
and flow volume again
that's wrong because
gravity is always pulling
pulling blood towards the
bottom of the lungs so
hydrostatic pressure would
be the highest at the
bottom not at the apex
leaving choice c as a
correct choice alveolar
pressure can exceed pulmonary
arterial pressure
potentially compressing
local capillaries and
severely limiting blood flow
so that of course is
not great either because
then we have no gas
exchange so we have a
ton of air sitting in
the alveolar spaces
but there's no blood
flow to pick that up so
that's not ideal
either but that is
the situation at
the apex of the lung
um when would the situation
be different if the recruit
was laying down so then
we don't have then those
zones of west break down
so it's really important um
with these questions that the
person is standing because
only then um the apex of
the lungs would be in terms
of gravity above the heart
right thank you and once
again as always updated
resources can be found in the
class preparation guide
I stay very close to the
physiology book and the
respiratory chapter that chapter
in Constanzo as I always
point out has a great summary
section that I would like
you to look at and it also
has self quizzing um
questions and the answers for
those are as always at the
end of the book and if you
have questions beyond that
you can always ask me before
i forget scholar x is also
a good resource um the
ones that pertain to this
lecture are also in the cpg
thank you again for
listening and if you have any
comments or suggestions
please let me know go to
the survey monkey and let
us know what you liked
and what i could have
done better thank you bye